Guide to the John Rogers Photograph Collection 1860-1927, undated PR 122
New-York Historical Society
John Rogers Photograph Collection
1860-1927, undated
New-York Historical Society
Rogers, John, 1829-1904
PR 122
3.5 Linear feet (6 boxes)
Collection of photographs portraying sculptor John Rogers, his family, residence, studio and sculpture groups. Included are photographs of sculpture by other artists.
Provenance
Gifts of Katherine Rebecca Rogers in 1936, 1937, 1955, 1956; gifts of Adelaide Hegeman Rogers in 1949 and 1955.
Access Restrictions
Materials in this collection may be stored offsite. For more information on making arrangements to consult them, please visit www.nyhistory.org/library/visit.
Biographical Note
John Rogers was a prominent American sculptor of the second half of the nineteenth century. The popularity of his work was unprecedented among American sculptors; between 1860 and 1893 he sold approximately eighty-thousand works. His success has been credited to his keen marketing as well as to his passion for addressing themes close to the heart of middle class Americans. Rogers eschewed classical sculpture styles and instead produced extremely detailed, narrative sculpture groups that focused on themes of everyday American life, popular literature, and the Civil War. Cast in plaster in order to be affordable, the Rogers Groups were renowned for their wit, humor, and sentimentality.
Born in Salem, Massachusetts in 1829, Rogers counted among his ancestors several generations of New England clergymen and merchants. Rogers's immediate family, however, was not particularly wealthy, and discouraged their son's early artistic efforts on the grounds that the life of an artist would not provide a sufficient salary. Instead, Rogers began working as a machinist and draftsman. He lived in various regions of the country in the course of his career, finally rising to the rank of master mechanic for the Hannibal and St. Joseph Rail Road in Hannibal, Missouri in 1856. He lost this job in the money panic of 1857. Having time on his hands, Rogers decided to give in to his artistic aspirations and traveled Europe in 1858 to study with the masters. His experiences in Paris and Rome were discouraging. He disliked the predominant classical styles that were taught and discovered that even the finest American artists found it difficult to make a living from their work. After only a year abroad, he returned to Chicago to become a draftsman again, leaving behind his hopes of becoming an artist.
In Chicago in 1859, he was encouraged by a friend to submit a small sculpture for a church auction. The piece he submitted, Checker Players, attracted enough attention that within months Rogers decided to move to New York and become a professional artist. There he met with some initial resistance in getting his work into shops. To gain publicity, he hired an African American to sell his anti-slavery work, Slave Auction, in the streets of New York, eventually drawing the notice of prominent abolitionists in the spring of 1860. Within the year he had made a name for himself and was getting positive reviews in the New York press. Stores were eager to stock his groups.
Rogers worked in plaster to keep production costs down and make his sculpture affordable. However, as orders increased, he became frustrated by the slowness and poor workmanship of his plaster casters. He endeavored to learn the trade himself and late in 1860 set up his own workshop, cutting costs and improving output. Although Rogers would produce some works in bronze and marble during his career, he would always be best known for his widely distributed plaster casts.
In the following years, he was increasingly successful. He broadened the audience for his work by placing groups in stores in Boston and Philadelphia. He began advertising in catalogs and periodicals and experimenting with packing methods so he could ship his works long distances. His works addressed a variety of themes, but those addressing the Civil War or portraying comical or literary scenes met with the most success.
In 1864, as his professional success grew, Rogers met and soon after married Harriet Moore Francis, a music teacher at Miss Haines' Gramercy Park Boarding School for Young Ladies. In 1866 they had their first child and began spending summers in New Canaan, Connecticut. By 1877 the family had built a house and made New Canaan their permanent home, returning to New York only occasionally. In New Canaan, Rogers built a studio adjacent to his house in which he sculpted the majority of his later works.
The Rogers Groups flourished in popularity through the 1870s and 1880s, but by 1889, the business began to go into decline as realism went out of fashion. Rogers, however, continued with his creative studio work, and produced one of his most acclaimed figures, a life-sized Abraham Lincoln, in 1892. Lincoln won a bronze medal the following year at the World's Columbian Exposition in Chicago.
Rogers suffered through the late 1890s from a progressive illness and died in 1904. Although he is not remembered as a great classical artist, his ability to bring the appreciation of sculpture to a wide audience of Americans was considered revolutionary.
Scope and Content Note
The John Rogers Photograph Collection spans the period from 1860-1927 and primarily contains photographs and documents relating to the family life and artistic career of John Rogers. Also included are photographs of other artists' work collected by Rogers, and photographs of famous acquaintances whose likenesses he sculpted.
Arrangement
The collection is divided into three series based on subject:
Missing Title
Series I: Personal Photographs
Series II: Sculpture by Rogers
Series III: Sculpture by Other Artists
Related Material at The New-York Historical Society
Within the Department of Prints, Photographs, and Architectural Collections, additional images of John Rogers and Rogers family members are available in the Cased Photograph File (PR 012), certificates given to Rogers at various exhibitions are in the Certificate File (PR 014), a 1939 calendar showing Rogers sculpture groups is located in the Calendar File (PR 146) and an album containing photographs of Rogers and his sculpture groups is available in the Album File (PR 002-12). For correspondence, published catalogs, and promotional materials relating to John Rogers, see Miscellaneous Manuscripts Rogers in the New-York Historical Society Library. Bronze masters and plaster Rogers Groups are available for study in the Henry Luce III Center of The New-York Historical Society. For further information on John Rogers' life and work, see David H. Wallace. John Rogers: The People's Sculptor. (Middletown, Connecticut: Wesleyan University Press: 1967).
New Canaan (Conn.); Cartes-de-visite (card photographs); Glass negatives.; Stereographs.; Lithographs.; Photographic prints.; Rogers, Ellen Derby, 1828-1894; Rogers, Frances Stetson, 1844-1923; Rogers, Harriet Francis, 1841-1927; Rogers, Henry Bromfield, 1837-1872; Rogers, John, 1800-1884; Rogers, John, 1829-1904; Rogers, John, 1866-1919; Rogers, Laura Derby, 1834-1907; Rogers, Laura Derby, 1879-1897; Rogers, Sarah Ellen Derby, 1805-1877; Sherman, William T. (William Tecumseh), 1820-1891 -- Portraits; Whittier, John Greenleaf, 1807-1882 -- Portraits; Ball, Thomas, 1819-1911; Beecher, Henry Ward, 1813-1887 -- Portraits; Beecher, Henry Ward, 1813-1887; Calverley, Charles, 1833-1914; Conkey, Samuel; Hartley, Jonathan Scott, 1845-1912; Perry, Martha Rogers, 1840-1925; Rogers, Alexander Parker, 1874-1950; Rogers, Charles Francis, 1870-1947; Rogers, Derby F., 1871-1955; Rogers, Elizabeth Bromfield, 1837-1872
- Series I: Personal Photographs
  Scope and Contents note
  Series I is divided into two subseries: People and Places. Thereunder, photographs are arranged alphabetically by name of individual or place. The photographs date from 1860-1927; many materials are undated. Photographs are arranged in two subseries: People, filed alphabetically by name; and Places, filed alphabetically by name. Glass negatives of the Rogers' residence in New Canaan, Connecticut, are filed at the end of the series.
  The People subseries consists of portraits of John Rogers, members of his family, and a few other notable figures. Family photographs include those of Rogers's parents, John Rogers (1800-1884) and Sarah Ellen Derby Rogers; some of his siblings, Ellen Derby Rogers, Laura Derby Rogers (1834-1907), Henry Bromfield Rogers (1837-1872), Martha Rogers Perry, Elizabeth Bromfield Rogers, and Frances Stetson Rogers; his wife, Harriet Francis Rogers; his children, Katherine R. Rogers, John Rogers (1866-1937), Laura Derby Rogers(1879-1897), Derby Rogers, Charles F. Rogers, and Alexander Parker Rogers. Photographs of paintings document earlier ancestors of Rogers, three of whom shared the name John Rogers (living from 1500-1555, 1572-1636, and 1666-1745) and one with the variant name John Rodgers who lived in the 18th century. Portraits of other members of the Derby, Jewitt, and Rogers families are also included. Portraits of prominent figures include abolitionist Henry Ward Beecher, General William Tecumseh Sherman, and poet John Greenleaf Whittier.
  The Places subseries includes photographs of the family home that Rogers built in 1877 in rural New Canaan, Connecticut, as well as of the detached studio that he later built on the same property. A lithograph of an unidentified New Canaan building is also included. At the end of this subseries are eight glass negatives of the residence, some of which include Rogers family members. Prints made from these negatives are available in the residence folder with the exception of those which are referred to as Rogers Family at Residence, for which there are no prints.
  - People
    - Beecher, Henry Ward(1813-1887), undated (Offsite-box 1, Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Cabot, Lillie, undated (Offsite-box 1, Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Derby, Martha Coffin (b. 1814), undated (Offsite-box 1, Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Derby, George, 1871 (Offsite-box 1, Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Derby, John, undated (Offsite-box 1, Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Francis, David (1779-1853), undated (Offsite-box 1, Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Jewitt Family, undated (Offsite-box 1, Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Mason, Hannah Rogers (1806-1872), undated (Offsite-box 1, Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Perry, Martha Rogers (1840-1925), 1866, undated (Offsite-box 1, Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Perry, Nellie, undated (Offsite-box 1, Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Rodger, John (18th Century), undated (Offsite-box 1, Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Rogers Family--Group Portraits (19th Century), undated (Offsite-box 1, Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Rogers Family--Group Portraits (20th Century), 1917-1927, undated (Offsite-box 1, Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Rogers, Alexander Parker (1874-1950), 1877 (Offsite-box 1, Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Rogers, Charles F. (1870-1947) (Offsite-box 1, Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Rogers, Derby (1872-1955), 1872-1900 (Offsite-box 1, Box 1, Folder 16)
      General note
      See also: Box 2, folders 48-49
    - Rogers, Elizabeth Bromfield (1844-1924), undated (Offsite-box 1, Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Rogers, Ellen Derby (1828-1894), undated (Offsite-box 1, Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Rogers, Frances Stetson (1844-1923), undated (Offsite-box 1, Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Rogers, Harriet Francis (1841-1927), 1860, 1864, undated (Offsite-box 1, Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Rogers, Henry Bromfield (sculptor's uncle), undated (Offsite-box 1, Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Rogers, Henry Bromfield (1837-1872), undated (Offsite-box 1, Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Rogers, Henry Bromfield, Jr. (b. 1867), undated (Offsite-box 1, Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Rogers, John (1500-1555), photograph of painting, undated (Offsite-box 1, Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Rogers, John (1572-1636), photograph of painting, undated (Offsite-box 1, Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Rogers, John (1666-1745), photograph of painting, undated (Offsite-box 1, Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Rogers, John (1800-1884), undated (Offsite-box 1, Box 1, Folder 27)
    - Rogers, John (1829-1904)--Portraits, 1860-1864, undated (Offsite-box 1, Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Rogers, John (1829-1904)--Portraits in studio, undated (Offsite-box 1, Box 1, Folder 29)
    - Rogers, John (1829-1904)--Portrait with group of artists, undated (Offsite-box 1, Box 1, Folder 30)
    - Rogers, John (1866-1937), 1868-1870, 1917, undated (Offsite-box 1, Box 1, Folder 31)
    - Rogers, Katherine R. (1868-1919), 1870-1872, 1917, undated (Offsite-box 1, Box 1, Folder 32)
    - Rogers, Laura Derby (1834-1907), [1860] (Offsite-box 1, Box 1, Folder 33)
    - Rogers, Laura Derby (1879-1897), [1895] (Offsite-box 1, Box 1, Folder 34)
    - Rogers, Sarah Ellen Derby (1805-1877), 1860, undated (Offsite-box 1, Box 1, Folder 35)
    - Sherman, William Tecumseh (1820-1891), undated (Offsite-box 1, Box 1, Folder 36)
    - Whittier, John Greenleaf (1807-1892), undated (Offsite-box 1, Box 1, Folder 37)
    - Unidentified, undated (Offsite-box 1, Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Places
    - Residence of John Rogers, New Canaan, Connecticut, [1885], undated (Offsite-box 1, Box 1, Folder 39)
    - Studio of John Rogers, New Canaan, Connecticut, undated (Offsite-box 1, Box 1, Folder 40)
    - Unidentified house, New Canaan, Connecticut, undated (Offsite-box 1, Box 1, Folder 41)
    - Glass negatives of residence, New Canaan, Connecticut (taken by Alexander P. Rogers)--Exterior, undated (Box 2, Folder 42)
    - Glass negatives of residence, New Canaan, Connecticut (taken by Alexander P. Rogers)--Interior, undated (Box 2, Folder 43-44)
    - Glass negatives of residence, New Canaan, Connecticut (taken by Alexander P. Rogers)--Rogers family at residence, undated (Box 2, Folder 45-47)
    - Glass negatives of residence, New Canaan, Connecticut (taken by Alexander P. Rogers)--Derby Rogers in library, undated (Box 2, Folder 48)
    - Glass negatives of residence, New Canaan, Connecticut (taken by Alexander P. Rogers)--Derby Rogers in parlor, undated (Box 2, Folder 49)
- Series II: Sculpture by Rogers
  Series II is arranged alphabetically by title of work and dates from 1862-1892; many photographs are undated. These titles correspond to the titles engraved by Rogers on his groups; works portraying people are listed under the individual's full name. A set of promotional photographs of the civil war Rogers Groups published by Maurice Stadtfeld and photographs showing more than one sculpture have been filed at the end of the series. Stereographs, cartes-de-visite, and cabinet cards produced for promotional purposes make up the bulk of this series, but modern prints and other non-promotional prints are also included. Works from throughout his career are represented. Oversize images of some works are available in Box 6.
  - Air Castles (1862), 1862, undated (Offsite-box 3, Box 3, Folder 50)
  - The Bugle Call (1886) (Offsite-box 3, Box 3, Folder 51)
  - The Bushwhacker / The Wife's Appeal for Peace (1865), [1865-1876] (Offsite-box 3, Box 3, Folder 52)
  - The Camp Fire / Making Friends With the Cook (1862), [1863] (Offsite-box 3, Box 3, Folder 53)
  - Camp Life: The Card Players (1862), 1863-1868 (Offsite-box 3, Box 3, Folder 54)
  - Challenging the Union Vote (1869), [1869]-1876 (Offsite-box 3, Box 3, Folder 55)
  - The Charity Patient (1866), 1866-1872 (Offsite-box 3, Box 3, Folder 56)
  - Checker Players (1860), 1865-[1876] (Offsite-box 3, Box 3, Folder 57)
  - Chess (1889), undated (Offsite-box 3, Box 3, Folder 58)
  - Coming to the Parson (1870), [1871] (Offsite-box 3, Box 3, Folder 59)
  - Council of War (1868), [1868-1876], undated (Offsite-box 3, Box 3, Folder 60)
  - Country Post Office (1863), 1863-[1876] (Offsite-box 3, Box 3, Folder 61)
  - Courtship in Sleepy Hollow (1868), [1868-1876] (Offsite-box 3, Box 3, Folder 62)
  - Faust and Marguerite: Their First Meeting (1890), undated (Offsite-box 3, Box 3, Folder 63)
  - Faust and Marguerite: Leaving the Garden (1891), undated (Offsite-box 3, Box 3, Folder 64)
  - Fighting Bob (1889) (Offsite-box 3, Box 3, Folder 65)
  - The First Ride (1888) (Offsite-box 3, Box 3, Folder 66)
  - The Fisher Girl (1860), undated (Offsite-box 3, Box 3, Folder 67)
  - Flower Box (1876), undated (Offsite-box 3, Box 3, Folder 68)
  - The Foundling (1870) (Offsite-box 3, Box 3, Folder 69)
  - The Fugitive's Story (1869), [1870] (Offsite-box 3, Box 3, Folder 70)
  - Going for the Cows (1873) (Offsite-box 3, Box 3, Folder 71)
  - Hide and Seek: Whoops (1874) and Hide and Seek (1875), [1875], undated (Offsite-box 3, Box 3, Folder 72)
  - The Home Guard / Midnight on the Border (1865), [1865-1876] (Offsite-box 3, Box 3, Folder 73)
  - Ichabod Crane and the "Headless Horseman" (1887), undated (Offsite-box 3, Box 3, Folder 74)
  - John Eliot Preaching to the Indians (1887-1890), 1890, undated (Offsite-box 3, Box 3, Folder 75)
    See also: Box 6, folder 126
  - Lafayette, undated (Offsite-box 3, Box 3, Folder 76)
  - Lambert, Mrs. Edward W. (ca. 1875), undated (Offsite-box 3, Box 3, Folder 77)
  - Landing of the Norsemen (1893), [1893], undated (Offsite-box 3, Box 3, Folder 78)
  - Lincoln, Abraham (1892) (Offsite-box 4, Box 4, Folder 79)
  - Madame, Your Mother Craves a Word With You (1886) (Offsite-box 4, Box 4, Folder 80)
  - Mail Day (1864), [1864-1876] (Offsite-box 4, Box 4, Folder 81)
  - Marguerite and Martha: Trying on the Jewels (1891) (Offsite-box 4, Box 4, Folder 82)
  - Nightmare (1857), undated (Offsite-box 4, Box 4, Folder 83)
  - Paez, Jose Antonio (1890), undated (Offsite-box 4, Box 4, Folder 84)
  - Parting Promise (1870) (Offsite-box 4, Box 4, Folder 85)
  - The Picket Guard (1861), [1863] (Offsite-box 4, Box 4, Folder 86)
  - Polo (1879), undated (Offsite-box 4, Box 4, Folder 87)
  - Private Theatricals / Last Moments Behind the Scenes, undated (Offsite-box 4, Box 4, Folder 88)
  - Returned Volunteer / How the Fort Was Taken (1864), [1864-1876] (Offsite-box 4, Box 4, Folder 89)
  - Reynolds, John Fulton (1884), [1884], undated (Offsite-box 4, Box 4, Folder 90)
  - Rip Van Winkle at Home (1871), [1875] (Offsite-box 4, Box 4, Folder 91)
  - Rip Van Winkle on the Mountain (1871), [1875], undated (Offsite-box 4, Box 4, Folder 92)
  - Rip Van Winkle Returned (1871), [1872] (Offsite-box 4, Box 4, Folder 93)
  - Rogers, John (1866-1939), bust (1871), undated (Offsite-box 4, Box 4, Folder 94)
  - Rogers, Sarah Ellen Derby (1862), undated (Offsite-box 4, Box 4, Folder 95)
  - The School Examination (1867), 1867-[1876] (Offsite-box 4, Box 4, Folder 96)
  - Sharp Shooters (1862), [1863]-1872 (Offsite-box 4, Box 4, Folder 97)
  - The Shaughraum and "Tatters" (1875) (Offsite-box 4, Box 4, Folder 98)
  - Sheridan, Philip Henry, [1895] (Offsite-box 4, Box 4, Folder 99)
  - The Slave Auction (1859), [1863-1876] (Offsite-box 4, Box 4, Folder 100)
    See also: Box 6, folder 127
  - Stark, John (1889), [1889], undated (Offsite-box 4, Box 4, Folder 101)
  - Taking the Oath and Drawing Rations (1866), [1866]-1872 (Offsite-box 4, Box 4, Folder 102)
  - The Town Pump (1862), [1863]-1872 (Offsite-box 4, Box 4, Folder 103)
  - Uncle Ned's School (1866), [1866]-1872 (Offsite-box 4, Box 4, Folder 104)
  - Union Refugees (1863), [1863-1876] (Offsite-box 4, Box 4, Folder 105)
  - Vase (1876) (Offsite-box 4, Box 4, Folder 106)
  - The Village Schoolmaster (1860), [1863] (Offsite-box 4, Box 4, Folder 107)
  - Washington, George (1875) (Offsite-box 4, Box 4, Folder 108)
  - We Boys (1872), [1872], undated (Offsite-box 4, Box 4, Folder 109)
  - Weighing the Baby (1876) (Offsite-box 4, Box 4, Folder 110)
  - Williams, John Earl (1870), undated (Offsite-box 4, Box 4, Folder 111)
  - The Wounded Scout / A Friend in the Swamp (1864), [1864-1876] (Offsite-box 4, Box 4, Folder 112)
  - Wounded to the Rear / One More Shot (1864) (Offsite-box 4, Box 4, Folder 113)
  - Set of Photographs of Civil War Rogers Groups (1859-1865), taken and published by Maurice Stadtfeld, [1886] (Offsite-box 4, Box 4, Folder 114)
  - Photographs of multiple Rogers Groups, undated (Offsite-box 4, Box 4, Folder 115)
- Series III: Sculpture by Other Artists
  Series III is arranged into two subseries: Collected Photographs of Sculpture, arranged thereunder alphabetically by sculptor, and Works Frequently Misattributed to John Rogers, arranged thereunder alphabetically by common title. Collected Photographs of Sculpture includes photographs of sculpture by the following contemporaries of Rogers: Charles Calverley, Thomas Ball, and L. Fenwick. Also included is a set of photographs of famous sculpture published by the Photo-Gravure Co. of New York. The miscellaneous category includes photographs of unidentified, mostly European sculpture. Works Frequently Misattributed to John Rogers includes works that have been determined to be the work of other artists but have been referred to as the work of John Rogers in published sources in the past. These include works by J.S. Hartley, Samuel Conkey and other unidentified artists.
  - Collected Photographs of Sculpture
    - Ball, Thomas, monument of Daniel Webster, 1886 (Offsite-box 5, Box 5, Folder 116)
    - Calverley, Charles (1833-1914), undated (Offsite-box 5, Box 5, Folder 117)
    - Fenwick, Reverend L., Undated (Offsite-box 5, Box 5, Folder 118)
    - Photo-Gravure Co. of New York, published set of photographs of sculpture, undated (Offsite-box 5, Box 5, Folder 119)
    - Miscellaneous, undated (Offsite-box 5, Box 5, Folder 120)
  - Works Frequently Misattributed to John Rogers
    - Bronze Wreath of Leaves and Berries Surrounding Mirror, undated (Offsite-box 5, Box 5, Folder 121)
    - Fido, [1861] (Offsite-box 5, Box 5, Folder 122)
    - Garrison, William Lloyd, undated (Offsite-box 5, Box 5, Folder 123)
    - Lotta as the Marchioness, by J.S. Hartley, 1876 (Offsite-box 5, Box 5, Folder 124)
    - Trout Fishing, by Samuel Conkey, 1868 (Offsite-box 5, Box 5, Folder 125)
- From Series II. Sculpture by Rogers
  - John Eliot Preaching to the Indians (oversize - showing John Rogers), 1891 (Offsite-box 6, Box 6, Folder 126)
  - The Slave Auction (1859) and Uncle Ned's School (1866), [1863-1866] (Offsite-box 6, Box 6, Folder 127)